Level one, sessile. Movement isn't
really necessary to survive. Ask any
plant, fungi, or barnacle and you'll see
sessility can work perfectly [music]
fine. Despite being cool enough to be
the topic of this video, moving at high
speeds requires a ton of energy. So, if
you can acquire food and reproduce while
sitting in one spot, it's usually the
most optimal thing to do. Of course, no
organism is ever truly still. Even at
level one, there are loads of cellular
processes going on and growth is a type
of movement, just very slow one. The
fastest growing plant in the world is
bamboo, capable of growing 91 cm in a
single day. That's extremely quick for a
grass. But, of course, a human could
make that distance in one or two steps
and humans are not even close to some of
the fastest organisms we will cover
today. So, let's hurry our way up the
speed ladder of life, moving on to level
two, creepers. Locomotion is now on the
table. With the ability to move your
entire being, you can relocate to get
away from a dangerous environment or to
seek food. But, at level two, you're
basically going to be doing this as
slowly as possible. Slime molds release
pseudopods, these temporary finger-like
things that spread out at 0.005
km an hour in search for [music] food.
Then, they drag themselves towards that
food at 0.000005
km an hour. I'm going to put the freedom
units on screen though, hopefully you
don't need that to realize that this is
[music] extremely slow. But, you don't
need speed or even a brain to be clever.
If you place a slime mold in a maze and
food at the exit, the resulting
pseudopod will always form the shortest
path to the exit, concentrating their
growth towards the food with perfect
mathematical efficiency. Famously, a
study placed oatmeal over a map of
Japan, representing the major urban
centers. Then, by letting a slime mold
grow on it, found that the resulting
slime network matched up almost exactly
to the real Tokyo rail line, which were
carefully optimized by Japanese experts.
In level two, I'll also include some
slowpokes like earthworms and snails
that have muscular activity, but only
enough to inch around very slowly. The
dwarf seahorse is the slowest swimming
fish, moving at 0.0015
km an hour, slower than most snails.
There are also echinoderms like [music]
starfish and sea urchins, which can use
hydraulic pressures in their little tube
feet [music] to slowly walk across the
ocean floor. Though some of them can
actually kind of run, weirdly enough.
For the most part, level twos tend to
only move when necessary, but that
changes at level three, marchers. Okay,
so now we have some muscle activity and
usually a few limbs, maybe four, six, or
hundreds for any of my millipedes
watching this. Level threes can
consistently walk or climb and keep it
up enough to cover long [music]
distances, but there's still things that
we would perceive as slow moving. Like
tortoises, which move at 0.48 km an
hour, but can sprint at up to 1 km an
hour. Basically all the movement you
could ever need for going about your
day, but if anything's ever [music]
chasing you, it won't be enough to get
away. So, level threes tend to invest
mostly in other defenses like a hard
shell or camouflage, because this level
of movement still requires constant
fuel. Sloths combat this with a slower
metabolism. [music]
They can only climb at 0.8 km an hour,
but as a trade-off, they don't need to
eat nearly as much as other mammals
their size. Actually, most slow animals
have a slow metabolism for energy
conservation, that's why [music] they're
slow. The slowest primate, the slow
loris, paces itself at 1.8 km an hour to
sneak up on prey and are able to strike
more quickly. They produce venom from
their armpits and will lick their pits
to gain a venomous bite, making them the
only venomous primates. Human walking
speed is at the upper end of level three
at about 4.8 km an hour, and many of the
other leisurely stroll speeds of the
higher level creatures will fall in this
range as Because as we're about to get
into, speeds at level four and higher
can be a struggle to maintain even for
short periods. Like I said, moving
around takes a lot of energy, especially
when you need to spend that energy on
other things like metabolism, growth,
and sickness.
Speaking [clears throat] of, it's a new
year and I've made a resolution to
myself to take my health more seriously.
But I hate the process of waiting for a
doctor's office to be open, then being
put on hold just to wait weeks for my
appointment. Not to mention, it's always
a risk that a doctor isn't a good fit or
very trustworthy or compassionate at
all. That's the beauty of Zocdoc,
today's paid partner sponsor. Zocdoc is
a free website that helps you easily
book high-quality in-network doctors to
find someone you love. Whether it's
dermatology, dentistry, primary care, or
eye care or one of over 200 more
specializations, you can easily search
by specialty or symptom to build the
care team that's right for you. My
favorite part about Zocdoc is getting to
see doctors' real-time availability so
that you can book them instantly right
from your device, right from your bed.
You can choose to meet in person or on
video and get access quickly, usually
within 24 to 72 hours or sometimes even
on the same day. With thousands of
verified patient reviews, Zocdoc will
help you find the perfect doctor for you
so that you can feel confident about
who's giving you medical care. You can
visit the link zocdoc.com/danandblue
or click the link in the description or
scan the QR code on screen to learn
more. Thank you to Zocdoc for sponsoring
this video.
Okay, time to pick up some speed with
level four runners. Slow and steady wins
the race unless you're not in a proverb,
in which case fast wins most races,
obviously. At level four, speed comes
about with intention. [music]
Whether that be to chase prey, run as
prey, migrate long distances, or to race
home because you have to pee. It evolves
from biotic pressures stacked on top of
abiotic ones. Chickens can run at an
impressive 14 km an hour and are
notorious for being very hard to catch
due to their quick and flighty
movements. The black mamba can slither
up to 19 km an hour in short [music]
bursts, hunting with one of the
deadliest bites in the animal kingdom,
and they don't even need any limbs to do
so. Snakes [music] have a lot of
different ways that they can move,
involving friction and skin muscles,
dragging themselves forward at multiple
points, or slithering pushes that cancel
out sideways forces, leaving them to go
straight forward. The physics of it is
actually really [music] cool. Now,
humans on average can build up a sprint
to 19 to 24 km an hour. Our ancestral
prey was often much faster than us, but
we used our endurance to keep up and
tail them for long periods of time.
Bipedal running is far more calorie
efficient than running on four legs, and
so we could chase them [music] from a
distance for a long time before they
fell exhausted and we could surround
them as a group. We may not be the
fastest, but we are the best endurance
runners of all animals, maybe besides
horses. So, despite being level four, we
regularly ran after and hunted level
fives. The basilisk lizard also reaches
24 km an hour, and this speed lets it
Jesus walk across the water, using its
specialized foot flaps to make air
pockets that keep it from sinking. But,
the fastest reptile is the perentie, one
of Steve Irwin's favorites, an
Australian monitor lizard that can burst
at up to 40 km [music]
an hour, able to outrun and catch
rabbits. There are a lot of fish that
swim at level four, like salmon and
trout and blue sharks. You also get a
lot of big mammals as well. Imagine a
hippo chasing you at 30 km an hour, or a
grizzly bear at 40. In short bursts,
elephants can hit 40 km an hour as well.
On the upper end of this tier, you get a
lot of things, big and small, that can
easily outrun you or easily run you
down. But, perhaps not every one of us
faces this same limitation. In the 2009
World Championship in Athletics, between
the 60th and the 80th meter of the
100-meter dash, Usain Bolt was recorded
moving at 45 km an hour, the fastest a
human has [music] ever moved while being
powered by only their own bodies. It was
this same race where he achieved the
current 100-m dash world record of 9.58
seconds, dethroning [music] Usain Bolt
to become the fastest man alive. Yes, I
put the average human in level four, but
not all humans are average. With the
right genetics, lifetime of training,
and optimized practices, many
world-class sprinters can reach over 40
km an hour, which is too fast to be
moving in a school zone where I live.
But, at level five, many animals are
hitting this and more on any regular
Tuesday. Roadrunners can get up to 42 km
an hour, but unlike the cartoon, coyotes
can go up to 69 km an hour and catch
roadrunners pretty regularly. So, either
Wile E. is kind of a lousy coyote or the
roadrunner is the Usain Bolt of
roadrunners. Probably both. Here, we
also see the flight speed of most birds.
Flying is an absolute cheat code when it
comes to moving fast. soaring through
the skies allows birds to avoid nearly
every predator if they're careful.
Migratory birds like geese fly [music]
at 80 km an hour, allowing them to get
across the world in a fairly reasonable
amount of time for a yearly vacation. In
level five, you are one of the quickest
organisms in the world, but there are
still tons of them. So, I'm going to
give you the rundown or fly down or swim
down of some of my favorites. The
fastest flying insect is the dragonfly
with speeds of 58 km an hour, allowing
them to achieve the highest kill rate of
any predator at 97 to 98%. Black rhinos
can charge at up to 55 [music] km an
hour. White-tailed deer can burst at 64
km an hour. The fastest thoroughbred
horse has hit 71 km an hour, but a
horse's typical gallop can still be 45
km an hour. Like I said, horses are the
best endurance runners alongside humans.
The ability to go at such speeds for
such long times is remarkable,
especially for an animal that large.
There's a reason they served as our
primary vehicles before automotives. The
fastest domestic cat is the Egyptian
Mau, which can hit 48 km an hour, while
the fastest dog is the greyhound, going
up to 72 km an hour. Swimming is also a
bit of a cheat code when it comes to
speed, since you can keep propelling
yourself forward with your flippers, and
that speed carries forward as you float.
Orcas can get up to 56 km an hour, and
dolphins can hit 60. Mako sharks are the
fastest sharks at [music] 72 km an hour.
Flying fish can swim at up to 70 km an
hour to fly out of the water, sometimes
covering distances up to 400 m and
reaching heights 6 m above the water
surface. It also sucks to get slapped by
one flying over your boat. Amazingly
though, one of the fastest fish is the
tuna, which has been seen going over 80
km an hour. So, think about that next
time you turn them into a sandwich. But,
of course, we can go faster still. Level
six, super bursters. This is the highest
level of what an animal can achieve with
powered movement. Cheetahs are the very
image we picture when we think about
speed. It's actually unclear what their
top speed is. Different sources say
different things, but the highest
estimate is 130 km an hour, which would
be enough to easily pass cars on most
highways. [music] Their long legs and
sleek bodies are specialized for
sprinting in long strides, and their
claws work like running spikes to keep
them agile on difficult terrain. [music]
Now, pronghorns are the second fastest
land animal, able to reach 96 km an hour
and maintain this for long distances.
They have much more endurance than
cheetahs, so with the right head start
can outrun and outlast them. But,
cheetahs can accelerate from zero to 97
km an hour in only 3 seconds, famously
faster than a Ferrari. So, the culling
game between these speed demons is
actually [music] determined by stealth
rather than speed. It's about how close
the cheetah can sneakily close the gap
between them before the chase begins.
[music] There are other extremely fast
animals, notably the billfish super
family. Swordfish can reach speeds up to
97 km an hour, incredible for being
anywhere between 200 [music] and 1200
lb. Sailfish can leap from the water at
109 km an hour, mogging the flying fish
in this regard. And in their case, are
large and sharp nosed enough to severely
injure or kill people and even destroy
the hulls of ships. But the fastest
swimmer of all animals is the black
[music] marlin, recorded stripping off
the line of a fishing reel at 129
[music] km an hour. As for runners,
ostriches are the fastest animal on two
legs. Some report them being faster than
pronghorns, but the general estimate is
about 70 km an hour. A lot of ungulates
tend to rely on high speeds to escape
[music] bursting predators like gazelle
and blue wildebeest. The quarter horse
is a breed [music] named after their
ability to beat other horses in races of
a quarter mile or less, moving up to 81
km an hour, though their endurance seems
to fall off afterwards. The tiger beetle
only moves at 9 [music] km an hour, but
that's absolutely for a bug. In fact,
these things move so quickly while
they're chasing prey that their eyes
don't capture enough photons, so they
have to stop every now and then to
register their surroundings before
moving again. Tiger beetles move 125
[music] body lengths a second, which
often makes it look like they teleport
instantly for observers. Adjusting for
its size, it would be like a human
[music] running 300 km an hour, as fast
as a high-speed train. The sesame seed
mite moves 322 body [music] lengths a
second. And for being so tiny, they're
essentially going thousands of
kilometers a second, making them the
fastest animal relative to their size in
the world. Now, amongst flyers at level
six, we start to see velocities over
over km an hour very consistently. These
[music] same derpy pigeons waddling
around your city parks can reach up to
149 kilometers an hour. There's a reason
we bred them into our main form of
long-distance messaging back in the day.
The frigate bird has the largest
wing-to-body area ratio of any bird,
allowing it to hit 153 [music]
kilometers an hour. But, the fastest
bird in terms of pure flapping flight
speed is the white-throated [music]
needle-tailed swift at 169 kilometers an
hour. Nice. [music] At a close second is
the Eurasian hobby, which has been seen
reaching 160 kilometers an hour and
frequently seen at [music] times
outflying needle-tailed swifts. So, a
fast hobby will beat a slower [music]
swift. But, these flights are measured
in the air with their free-form
three-dimensional movement. In terms of
horizontal speed, the [music] fastest
flyer is actually the Mexican
free-tailed bat, which hits 160
kilometers an hour, beating out the
cheetah as the fastest [music]
mammal in the world. Now, believe it or
not, ducks can fly pretty fast, too.
Watch this one as it Oh, never mind.
That prairie falcon was faster.
Dive-bombing in at 100 kilometers an
hour, cracking its bones and concussing
it [music] in one fell swoop. But, you
may have heard of another falcon that
does this, not twice as fast, not three
times as fast, but four times faster. At
level seven, we supersede the limits of
muscles, wings, and standard biophysics
to become ballistic. The peregrine
falcon soars high, high up into the sky,
then stoops, launching into a high-speed
dive and tucking in its wings to become
an aerodynamic hunting missile that no
prey animal can escape. They falcon
punch medium-sized birds, which either
instantly die or are stunned mid-flight,
plummeting to their demise. As the
fastest animals on the planet, peregrine
falcons have been said to achieve close
to 400 kilometers an hour in their stoop
dives. Though an older study proposed
that a hypothetically ideal falcon could
potentially hit 625 km an hour. These
are insane amounts of speed bolstered by
constant acceleration due to gravity and
optimized aerodynamic form, letting them
reach speeds impossible to achieve with
powered flight alone. They've also been
found to use very similar tracking and
trajectory feedback systems as actual
military missiles. And I can't help but
notice that their profile matches up
with a B-2 bomber quite nicely. So, it's
safe to say they're quite optimized for
airborne warfare. The golden eagle can
also stoop dive. And while being less
maneuverable than peregrines due to
their large size, they still have been
observed reaching 320 km an hour and may
even be equal or superior to peregrine
falcons on average. It's both up to
debate and to the specific individual.
Realistically, most peregrine falcons
and golden eagles are going to be maxing
out their speeds under 200 km an hour,
which is still more than enough to chase
down and obliterate prey. But however
fast the Usain Bolt of peregrines and
golden eagles is, we have no idea.
Still, it's a safe bet to say that of
all living animals right now, the world
speed champion is a bird belonging to
one of these two species. To even
discuss comparable speeds in other
organisms, we have to shift to
non-locomotive movements. Hummingbird
wings can beat 80 times in a single
second in a unique [music] figure eight
pattern, letting them hover in the air
precisely and be the only birds that can
fly backwards. Trap-jaw ants have
spring-loaded jaws held back by latches.
When one of their trigger hairs are
touched, the latch releases, causing
mandibles to mechanically slam in at 250
km an hour and severely injure prey.
They can even use the force generated by
their jaws to catapult themselves,
popping through the air like popcorn in
order to escape and frighten predators.
Though Dracula ants have even faster
mandibles at 320 km an hour. The fastest
voluntary movement in humans is the
saccade, [music]
the tiny movements our eyes make in
order to adjust for reading and
tracking, which can reach angular
[music] speeds of 700° a second. It
allows our eyes to shift and focus
quickly, which is necessary for reading
and visual scanning. Spirostomum is a
single-celled ciliate that can shrink
itself to a quarter of its size [music]
50 times faster than the blink of an
eye, disappearing right in front of
predators, and hits an acceleration of
14 G. For reference, race cars
accelerate at 4 to 5 G, cheetahs at 4.7
G, and some rockets have reached 10
[music] G. Between 13 and 25 G is the
lethal range of G-force. It's a level of
speeding up that can actually kill you.
And the fastest accelerating organism in
the world, which reaches 20,000 G, grows
on poop. The most elite organism in the
world in terms of acceleration is the
dung cannon, also known as the hat
thrower fungus. Remember how cheetahs
accelerate from 0 to 90 km an hour in 3
[music] seconds? These fungi burst and
launch their sporangia from 0 to 90 km
an hour in 3 millionths of a second. And
because this [music] actually carries
fungal spores, that means it's really an
entire organism, or at least a
reproductive unit, accelerating at this
speed, far faster than any human
vehicle. In terms of all biological
movements, though, the fastest
acceleration in nature is [music] likely
from jellyfish stings, which come from
cells called nematocysts that fire tiny
harpoons reaching 5.4 million G. Nature
is seriously impressive [music]
and really, really fast. But as humans,
we've built vehicles that are faster, at
least in terms of velocity. The land
speed record belongs to the ThrustSSC,
that hit 1,228
km an hour, breaking the sound barrier
at Mach 1.06. [music]
The fastest manned aircraft is the North
American X-15, hitting 7,274
km an hour, or Mach 6.72. [music]
And the fastest any organism has ever
moved is 39,938
km an hour, when three crew members on
the Apollo 10 mission were descending
back to Earth from lunar orbit. With our
ability to create and use science,
humans have become the fastest
organisms. But considering the speeds
that some of the animals in nature are
capable of, especially while balancing
evolutionary constraints, makes their
feats incredible works of science on
their own. And who knows? Maybe
something long extinct has [music]
reached even higher speeds. Maybe
something in the wild out there today
hit a speed record that none of us were
there to observe. We'll never know
because we're not fast enough to catch
everything. Okay, just for fun, let's
scale some speedsters. Dash [music] from
The Incredibles, 650 km an hour. Speedy
Gonzales, 1,440 km an hour. A-Train,
1,609 [music]
km an hour. Quicksilver, just faster
than the speed of light. The Road
Runner, 3.1 [music] times the speed of
light. Sonic the Hedgehog has gone over
nine times the speed of light. The Flash
has done 10 trillion times the speed of
light. And of course, the cameraman that
films all of them, who can get up to
infinite light speeds. Okay, fast, hit
that subscribe button, and thanks for
watching.